Then I asked the management like can I
actually drop a level?
>> This is Igor, a senior staff engineer at
Meta, Google, and Cruz who wanted a
demotion.
>> You cannot still justify my level with
the project being completed.
>> He failed to get the demotion at Meta
and going back to Google at a lower
level was harder than expected.
>> They don't have a process for bringing
people at a level down, but they made it
possible for me. We went over that
experience and some transparent
discussion across levels. Which
engineering level has the best quality
of life?
>> There there are many things that can go
wrong when you share stuff like this.
>> What makes you willing to share?
Here's the full episode.
you mentioned in a post, a pretty famous
post that I'll link so people can see
that uh Meta didn't have a process for
demotion and you were looking for
demotion. Can you talk about what led
you to wanting a demotion at Meta?
>> Yeah. So when you join a big company
meta is not the exception here but you
you're joining a big company at a very
high level like a senior staff there are
certain expectations from uh your
performance right come performance
review like at ma it's called PSC uh you
you're being judged against other senior
staff engineers in the organization
right and uh and meta as of a year ago
they started to like lay off people like
you know they starting doing the Amazon
thing essentially like let's lay off the
10% lowest performance. So what it means
is that you have at most one year to
ramp up to to be comparable in
performance to other uh old-timers in
the company and also what what does it
even mean to be you know an E7
in a company like this right you need to
be an expert
uh a big expert in the field you need to
know a lot of people you need to
understand the infrastructure that you
working with very deeply. You probably
need to be easily familiar with like any
piece of code that you your team is
working with and also you need to know
all the surrounding like what all the
surrounding teams are doing and you need
to know all these people like all core
people around you and they need to know
you and they need to trust you right
that's a very difficult thing to achieve
um uh within like a relatively short
period of time I initially thought that
okay when when you so again joining Meta
day one, I know less than an intern
sitting next to me, you know, who spent
maybe two weeks who was hired two weeks
prior to me, right? So like I I start
from like level zero and then hopefully
like you you be able to get to something
that like L3 would perform. So like you
you can take some very easy task that
under supervision from other folks. You
can uh kind of get promote yourself to
like a junior engineer, right? Then then
you do some some more stuff. You learn
additional things. You can get promoted
to like a less junior engineer like a
E4. And then slowly you ramp up, you
know, to more and more of like higher
levels essentially like you start from
zero and and you climb the ladder as
fast as you can. Yeah. So you you you
ramp up yourself to you know the level
that you supposed to achieve and you
know the more senior you are the more
levels you need to jump through. And I
believe that uh within this uh year and
two months that I spent in meta, I maybe
if I'm generous with myself, I I maybe
achieved like E6. So I I don't feel like
I reached E7.
>> What did you see that made you think you
weren't living up to the expectations?
>> It's self judgment mostly, right? You
know, I this scale where we we we call
numbers. It's not like quantum states,
right? there there are many things in
the middle right it's a it's a
continuous scale so uh it's it's very
hard to say where you are on on on the
ladder but uh again cons comparing
myself to other senior stuff engineers
in the world that I knew uh I felt like
if if anybody going to be on a chopping
board that's going to be me right uh
Yes. And so that that was one thing
about uh about this uh you know ramp up
process. And the second thing I I also
noticed that I really enjoyed doing like
the coding stuff like just sitting down
debugging things like that what I really
loved about the job. So when I during my
ramp up when I was around like E5 E6 uh
territory that's what I really wanted to
do right. I I I felt like as a you know
as someone who was programming from age
of 12 I really like like coding
debugging uh designing
u mentoring more junior people but like
a senior stuff engineer it's it's more
than that. It's like a leader who like
you know spends most of the time in
meetings and design docs and touches
much less code and it's a slightly
different type of work and and and just
by by going through this process I
realized that actually I want to be
uh I want to be in the E5 E6 territory
and and then then I asked like the the
management like can I actually drop a
level and I understand that for for the
It's it's a difficult thing to implement
because I already have some granted
stock. I have a certain compensation
package. Um and so how do you like you
know how do you execute that? It's uh
it's not a well polished process. I I
know that they can uh switch levels when
you go from like one title to another.
So like let's say you were a director
and you want to become an AC. Um so they
do have some of that uh like demotion
process and I frankly I don't know how
they do it. Uh but yeah like staying in
the same uh job category and dropping
level just uh
like they said it's not possible.
>> I see. So when you asked if it's
possible for demotion um your manager
went to HR and kind of the the result
was just it's just an impossible thing
to do. you know, I asked a question and
I got the answer. No, maybe if I pushed
harder, if I like went to talk to the,
you know, VP or something, they would
have made it possible. But, uh, at the
same time, I,
uh, you know, I also felt like, uh, I'm
too far outside of my comfort zone. And
before
coming to Meta, I worked a little bit at
Cruz. And before that, I worked at
Google for uh, 14 and a half years. And
that was my comfort zone. I just had
this option that like the the easy way
out essentially like it's uh had a
recruiter who was contacting me
periodically like I already to come back
to Google. So this time I just said yeah
let's talk.
>> When you were at Google and at Cruz you
were at these senior levels as a senior
staff engineer. What's the difference
that makes it so that you can perform
there but not at at meta? So when I came
to Google, I started from the the lowest
uh E3 like L3 level. Uh so junior
software engineer and slowly over the
many years I raised through like
promotions
uh many times failing like to get
promoted and then you know a year or two
later asking again and then uh climbing
the ladder. My last promotion to senior
staff happened because I was able to
accomplish something big in the project
that uh I worked I I worked in that
project for several years. So I was
already like an expert. I knew everybody
right everybody knew me and I was able
to build something that I I can be proud
of. But uh again coming then then
leaving Google and going to cruise it
was also very difficult for me to ramp
up there because you coming starting
from zero and the first year was very
difficult for me in cruise but uh over
time I found like a
a relatively
safe uh like you know my my found some
comfort zone there until Cruz as a
company uh went uh bad like they had the
accident and then they had layoffs and
then uh like people were just quitting
all the time like losing people. So I
decided that I want to leave as well. Uh
but before before the accidented cruise
I actually was quite happy. Uh I was
able to do some coding. I was able to do
like mentoring of other folks and I was
able to also like act as an uberl a
little bit like you know um guiding the
team on things that you know they need
to do.
>> You successfully ramped up the senior
staff at Cruz and then at Meta was a bit
harder. What what were the differences
between those two ramp ups in your
opinion? uh Cruz was a smaller company
uh so less infrastructure to learn the
team uh is like less crowded space I
would say like you can easily carve out
space for you to grow into like you know
like there is
lack of people and you can say okay well
this project needs someone to work on
and and you can just go and work on on
this stuff at meta I felt like uh it's
quite crowded that like especially among
the senior fogs
um it felt a little bit like they have
too many frankly
um at least in the work where I worked
uh so I don't know about all of meta but
uh it it felt like the space is a little
bit crowded you need you need to find
scope for yourself
>> is there anything that you you would
have changed in your onboarding process
that could have made things different
>> probably uh again I didn't switch
companies that many times in my career I
started at Google spent so many years
there then I only switched like cruise
and then meta so I'm I'm not very well
experienced in switching companies and
essentially you know this whole ramp up
process is new to me and I also felt
like the management at meta also doesn't
know how to on support uh senior folks
because most of the senior folks in the
company they they grew within the
company to those senior levels. Even if
they came
uh to this specific org,
you know, from another org within meta,
but at least they
they already have the meta knowledge,
you know, like they know how to run a
job in a in a cluster, right? I think I
spent a lot of time just uh reading docs
and uh trying to like build this
foundational knowledge. I think I spend
too much time doing that. Like it much
it is much better to just get your hands
dirty and just try doing stuff like you
know and then and then like doing doing
those things in parallel like you you
build something accomplish some tasks
and also you're learning in parallel and
I and I did more of the learning part
less of the
>> the building.
>> Yeah. Is there something that you wish
was done or maybe something that would
have helped you from from the manager
side?
>> Just guiding me, right? If if they say
like, oh, this other person just ramped
up the like, you know, three three
quarters ago and here's what they did. I
would have followed that recipe. We just
didn't have the recipe. Like I I'm not I
don't have any complaints against my
management. Like they, you know, they
try to support me. the best they just
also lacked this uh expertise of like
ramping up with senior folks you know so
it's it was a learning experience for
all of us
>> I've heard um in conversations from
other people as well that I guess job
mobility as a senior IC actually be
becomes progressively riskier or maybe
scarier I guess because you get so used
to your existing org and all of that.
Um, is that something that you've seen
in other people or like peers and and as
well in that uh senior IC job mobility
is a lot tougher?
>> I've seen uh folks at Google that uh
left Google and then came back a year or
two later saying that it didn't work out
well for them. Um
I yeah it's you know people don't share
things like that openly usually. it's
it's much harder to to hear those
stories. You hear the success stories,
you don't hear the failures. Um also I
think that if I kept trying like instead
of going back to Google, I went to I
don't know some other company um I would
be much like you know more experienced
in ramping up and then maybe maybe if
you do this often enough uh it becomes a
a habit and and then and then you can do
it easily. You mentioned that you you
thought you weren't meeting expectations
based on your own judgments. Um I'm
curious, did you ever get any feedback
from your manager or anyone saying,
"Hey, you need to do more for your
level's expectations."
>> Yeah, I did get feedback. I just, you
know, don't necessarily want to openly
share all of that. Uh but uh yeah I I
was so in the part like just the few
months leading to my living meta I was
working on a project that uh initially I
thought it will take me like two weeks
to accomplish. It was like a small thing
that uh I thought would be easy to do
and turned out to be actually a lot more
involved and a lot more complicated
and I felt like
uh even if I finish it uh which I almost
did like I almost brought it to
completion
um even if I finish it and launch and
everything successful it is still not an
E7 level project. it it you cannot still
just justify my level with that project
being completed.
Probably it's my fault in like which
projects I pick uh you know or how I
underestimated the complexity of the
thing
>> because you're going back to Google. Um
are you going back to an org where you
have all the existing context and and
relationships and all of that?
>> No. No. Everything will be new to me.
new people, new infrastructure, new new
everything. Um, but at least I know, you
know, I know how Google operates. I know
the
uh, you know, the culture. There there
are differences in cultures also between
the companies. And I think that Meta
also like in in terms of internal
culture at Meta like I didn't feel it
like it fits me the best. What what's
the biggest cultural differences between
Meta and Google?
>> Meta tends to to set up very ambitious
goals. They give you like often times
they will give you very arbitrary
deadline saying like okay this project
uh you need to finish it within like you
know by September 15th whatever like 1
month from now and then everybody works
hard like there is a lot of pressure
like you need to constantly send the
updates to the leadership how the
project progresses comes uh the date the
deadline the project is still unfinished
and it just keeps dragging on and so
like what and everybody's fine with Uh
again I don't know I don't I haven't
seen all of meta I've seen the specific
org where I work and and it feels like
uh so then what what was the purpose of
setting this aggressive deadline right
then then like you know are we like you
know you can do it once but like after
five times going through this project
through this like artificial pressure
with like non-realistic goals then
people just say like okay you know what
5:00 p.m. I'm going home like I'm not
I'm not going to try to to to work hard
because I I know that there is like this
this whole pressure is artificial,
right? Um I think at Google is much more
reasonable in that uh regard like if if
there is a deadline uh it's probably for
good reasons and and people would like
would work hard but usually they will
not be pressure again talking about
Google like as of 10 years ago. I'm not
sure that it's still true today, but you
would be pressured to to fix something
or to accomplish something when there is
really
uh you know exceptional case for that
like you you wouldn't be pressured to to
to work under pressure
you know for years.
>> Yeah. I mean, I get the sense that the
industry as a whole is kind of becoming
a little bit more intense when it comes
to execution and deadlines. I've heard
some people saying that Google as well
has felt a little bit of pressure too,
but hard to say. It depends on the org,
I'm sure.
>> Yeah, could be. And again I I didn't
feel personally much pressure at Meta
but just talking to other folks seeing
how they they work and operate and uh as
I said there is this cultural thing
where the leadership wants like updates
and everything and then and then the the
people on the ground they actually
kind of dismiss it essentially like it's
it's like they you know it almost feels
like a elementary school like where the
P teacher is yelling But kids are still
playing. Like if you're yelling too
much, it's it's like uh it's it's
stops working essentially, right? If if
you if you constantly put pressure on
your people, uh it just doesn't work
anymore. Like so what do you do next?
You start laying off people. Yeah, it
might work for to some degree, but
again, people adjust to everything.
>> That's crazy. You mentioned that you
when you reached out to Google too you
you explicitly asked for kind of a
demotion or going back as a L6 when
before you were an L7. Was that a
challenge or was that just very
straightforward process with the
recruiter?
>> It was a challenge for the recruiter to
also make this happen because uh they
have a process for PE bringing people in
back at the same level or even like
level up. They don't have a process for
bringing people at a level down, but
they made it possible for me. Again, I
can totally see how like a person comes
back and says like I want to be a level
down. It's like there might be some red
flags. There might be uh you know things
that I'm not telling you know it's a
gamble for a manager to to hire a person
like that. also just by giving me offer
at the level down they understand that
it will be they will not be able to
match my compensation
you know at the previous place uh so so
like would I even accept it right and so
so I had to like
assure my recruiter that uh yes I'm
happy to accept the offer at the lower
compensation like you know a lot of
people will not do something like I did
because it's like it's a significant
drop in in compensation.
>> You mentioned um stuff that people might
be hiding from the recruiter. What comes
to mind when you you mention that? I
don't know maybe you maybe you did
something in the company that you know
you like a fireball offense or something
like I like I I don't know like it if if
you're a manager and somebody comes to
you with like you know saying like yeah
previously I was uh this level now I
want to be level below please hire me it
does sound fishy like why don't you like
what's wrong with you like
you know there are so many companies out
there like why why would you come back
to to this company like why don't you
try something else elsewhere like I I I
don't know what questions popped up in
my hiring manager's head uh when he saw
this
>> Google's current process do they do host
matching or what was the like did you
meet up with the hiring manager
beforehand or just through the recruiter
>> the recruiter sent me a few openings and
uh asked asked me which one sound
interesting. I spoke to a few hiring
managers.
Um, one was sound like sounded like the
best match for me and uh then I spoke to
a few engineers on the team. Then I
spoke to the manager's manager and uh
that was it. So another nice thing for
me is that they didn't require me to
reinter.
>> Oh, interesting. But it had been like
three years maybe
>> over Yeah. three and a half years. Uh so
yeah, they didn't ask me to reinter
uh that actually that was another
interesting thing that they said like if
if you're coming back as E7
uh you definitely don't need an
interview because you were already L7.
But if you're going to be like L6, then
you might need to do a coding interview
because who knows if you wrote code, you
know, while you were out.
>> That's kind of funny. Yeah, I got an
exception from coding.
>> I see. That's funny. You got promoted
out of competence in the lower levels.
>> Yes. But it's it's understandable when
people like go to higher levels, they
write less code and uh maybe they get
rusty. Who knows?
>> It's kind of crazy that you could
boomerang after it had been three years
or more.
>> Yeah. To be fair, I don't know if that's
a general Google's policy or it was just
a special case for me. I don't I don't
have any friends that did this uh
recently to to to understand if if like
they did it for anybody else.
>> You mentioned earlier that you know a
lot of people don't share this kind of
stuff about the motions and these types
of things and I'm curious what makes you
willing to share. I'm a generally very
open person like I I like sharing my my
life experiences positive and negative
with friends and uh you know I yeah I
generally quite open and also I'm quite
confident that's another thing like you
wouldn't share if you worried about your
career if you worried about uh uh you
know there there are many things that
can go wrong when you share stuff like
this right so Uh I'm I'm very privileged
essentially. I don't need the work visa.
So I can live in this country uh without
being attached to a certain employer. Uh
my spouse has uh health insurance. Uh my
kids are already grown up and uh off to
college and uh I don't have mortgage on
on my house. So like I I can afford not
to work for a few years. I can uh you
know I don't I I'm fine with like if
let's say I I said something in this uh
chat right now and and Google says we
don't want you for some reason like I'm
totally fine. I will just
so that that's a that's a position of
privilege, right?
>> Definitely. I mean you're you're free.
Yeah. You're entirely free. You're your
own person which is awesome.
>> Yeah. So that's that's a position of
privilege that many other people
wouldn't have. So I
if if another person asked me like
should I post about my challenges at
work, I would probably say no. Like
unless you feel so so safe and secure.
>> And I you mentioned at Google you were
asking for promos. You went from their
lowest level up and you were pushing and
pushing for promos. And that's a very
different mindset from now which you
were kind of pushing for demotion. I'm
curious is there did something major
change that made you um not motivated to
go for promos anymore in your career?
Essentially if if you are an a senior
engineer right at E5 or E4 you don't
even know like what's the life of like
two levels above you looks like right
you you probably you can imagine what
what happens at like one level above you
but but it's
it's very hard to see like what what
does a principal engineer do like most
people don't know and uh I don't know by
going through this Like I realized that
my happiest time was uh when I was like
working in a relatively small team uh
doing a lot of coding uh debugging
designing
mentoring more junior folks that's
that's where I felt the happiest.
>> Let's say money is not a constraint at
all and it was just which engineering
level has the best quality of life in
your opinion? Which one would you say?
>> Uh senior uh engineer like E5, L5. Uh
yeah, that's probably
least pressure. you're still shielded by
uh you know probably like if if you're
working on a team you probably have an a
TL who is E6 on the team who you know
sends all the updates to the upper
levels like and and shields the the
lower like the team from all the stuff
you have the management uh also like the
lower level managers who shield you from
all this stuff. Uh so you can just uh
do the stuff that hopefully you enjoy
what you're doing like not not everybody
enjoys doing work like a lot of people
do it just for money but I personally I
was programming since I was uh 12 years
old. So I I really like this stuff. I
got into this job because I love it and
it happens to pay well. So like but I
would do it even if it wasn't paying
well. Like a lot of people come to
software engineering because just
because that's the money thing.
>> So then if it was easy uh as easy to do
it would your ideal situation be two
levels of demotion?
>> That's too extreme. I I think I can I I
I think I can still enjoy being like E6
I quite quite comfortable with and maybe
I haven't been E7 long enough to to like
to get comfortable in the in the in the
role like maybe if I just kept doing it
for some time longer
I would have started enjoying it.
>> Yeah.
like you know one uh thing is like was I
was I really like you know uh imposter
syndrome is something that everybody has
regardless of what you'll ever list. I'm
sure Elon Musk has imposter syndrome. U
so you know I'm I'm questioning myself
like was I really
you know qualified to do to be E7 and my
answer is like partially yes but not
fully. It's like a multi-dimensional
thing and in some dimensions I probably
was good and in some dimensions was not
as good.
>> You mentioned working with other peer
IC's that were also really high level.
Um is there skills that you saw that
they had which would have closed the gap
for you personally or um something that
you thought made them so strong?
>> It's often a mistake to compare yourself
against a group of people like that.
That's what uh gives you a lot of uh
imposttor syndrome where you're saying
like oh those people around me they're
so smart they are so good at talking
they're so good at doing presentations
they're so good at communicating they're
so good at leading but turns out that
it's like one person is good at this
another person is good at this and like
you you're comparing yourself against
like a team of people and so that's uh
that's always you need to be careful not
to make that mistake.
So yeah, I I I think I I you know, given
enough ramp up time, I would have been
able to reach like full productivity and
being useful to the company at E7. I
just felt like I like I I was not
enjoying the ride essentially and I
didn't have to like and and I debated a
lot before before making the decision to
leave, right? I was talking to friends.
I was talking to family. And pretty much
everybody was telling me like, "Are you
crazy? Like, you're not laid off yet.
You're not Nobody showed you the door.
Why would you do something crazy like
that?" And and even if you're leaving
like you don't enjoy it, why why won't
you try E7 elsewhere? Like why do you
need to go level down? That that's there
is a lot of peer pressure. And my answer
to that was just like, "Yes, I can try
that. I can do that, but I like I don't
want that, right? It's like why why I'm
capable of running a marathon, but I
don't like running a marathon. I don't
like running. So, like why why would I
do that?
>> You mentioned that you kind of rose
through the ranks at Google. I'm kind of
curious what what was the project that
got you promoted to senior staff at
Google? It
>> was a project in ads. Um ads builds a
lot of machine learning infrastructure.
Uh because like you know the ranking of
ads is a essentially recommendation
system. Um and uh
I was working on this machine learning
infra and uh when I came to that team
they were doing training on CPUs not on
GPUs but on CPUs and uh TPU was a new
thing new new hardware that Google was
developing.
uh it was about to be released like
maybe
uh a year or two be you know when I
joined the team and my my role was to
make sure that this ads uh training
infrastructure can run on those TPUs and
uh
uh additionally when you train machine
learning models
uh the scale matters and uh the
utilization matters and uh there are
lots of um there are lots of nuances
that uh can like you know your your
model may be training but uh things go
wrong
um it's online training which is also
like something that most people don't
know like LLMs don't usually train in
online training mode so there are lots
of experience on the team uh like the
the whole infrastructure that existed
within that team was built for the CPU
training And it was polished over I
don't know over 10 years. Uh it was
polished to be super reliable, super
like you well monitored the unit tested.
Everything is like very rigid, very like
polished, right? And here I am coming
and building a completely new piece of
infrastructure to run on TPUs
and it it has to be as good as as the
old you know as polished as as monitored
as tested as reliable. Um so it was a
big project and uh you know it
succeeded. Yeah, it it's something to be
like I was proud of what I built and so
that got me promoted.
>> What was the operating model of that
project? Were you TL or were you kind of
writing a lot of it yourself or how
would you describe the execution?
>> Yeah, initially it was like a quite
exploratory project. So it was just two
P people. I was the TL plus one person
uh to building like a prototype plus a
lot of people from other teams helping
like the TPU team, the compiler team,
the like there are lots of other people
who were helping us succeed like the
TensorFlow team we were writing in
TensorFlow back then u you know there
so it's it's also like where you need
credibility like that's that's why
knowing people and them knowing you is
very important like trusting you uh if
if you don't have that you cannot
succeed. So it's it's a really like
cross team collaboration uh very big
project and uh again hardware like this
you need to decide how many of these
chips you want to order
uh and they will be delivered like 18
months from now
before and right now you don't have any.
It's not like you can like try out and
and see. So like and those chips are
super expensive, right? Uh so
it's a it's a very risky thing to do for
the company and uh yeah it's like
a a lot of uh risk takingaking a lot of
like leadership skills that they needed
for for doing stuff like that. So you
were on the well well kind of the
product team not actually product you
were machine learning infra for the ads
org and then all the underlying infra
teams were helping collaborate with you.
Yeah you mentioned compilers maybe some
training infra other infrastructure
teams. Yeah. And once the things started
working a little bit, uh the team grew
quite a bit more. A lot more people
joined the effort and like started like
working polishing and then again like
first generation TPUs comes in and then
they already tell you like we already
designed the next generation who will be
coming you know next year. Uh so you're
already rushing to you know adjust your
infrastructure to the next thing and and
that's like pretty much every year you
you're like upgrading your
infrastructure.
>> How did you test the initial builds of
this infrastructure if you didn't have
the chips to begin with? A a lot of
things were just about like input
reading and processing which you can do
without having the chips like the the
the difference between CPU training
where you have uh you have the CPU
and uh Intel CPU they can do floating
point arithmetic and integer arithmetic
in parallel.
So and and the floating point arithmetic
is relatively slow. So input reading and
processing was free on the same CPU.
Um going from that mode of operation to
you have a relatively
uh weak uh computer with eight TPU
chips. Each one of those TPU chips is
like order of magnitude faster than the
CPU uh that you had before. If several
orders I think it's like two orders of
magnitude faster.
uh now there is no chance you can do the
input reading on the host of the of
those TPU of those TPUs. So you you need
to like build the the input processing
pipelines and everything. But that's
something you can test uh outside of uh
like without having TPUs. Actually we
did many times we did this test where
people say uh next TPU will be like two
times more performant than the previous
one. Um
and a nice test to test your
infrastructure is to say like okay we
will just remove all all computation
from our models just let's see how fast
we can you know feed the data in take
the outputs out and and process this
whole thing like how fast your system
can run if if the TPU was infinitely
fast and that's a nice test uh to to do
uh to see that um
you know you you don't have bottlenecks
and you do find a lot of bottlenecks all
the time like things that previously
were like like thing that schedules like
uh which data to to train on it's uh you
know previously was never like an issue
and then suddenly this is your
bottleneck in the model uh and and and
and and many many things like that. So
if I'm understanding correctly, the the
TPU consumes data orders of magnitude
faster than the CPU one. So everything
around the processing unit like the data
loading and maybe I don't know the
scheduling and all the other things that
are around the TPU needed to be scaled
and tested and that's a lot of what you
did to get promoted. Is that right?
>> Yeah. Plus you know there there are
always like funny things that you get
where like certain resources are more
available than other resources. Uh for
example so you you know you're training
on some insane amount of data pabytes of
data. Uh this data is stored on spinning
discs because there is like not enough
SSDs in the world. So spinning discs uh
if if you look at the history of
spinning discs they getting bigger in
terms of storage space but um the speed
at which they rotate is is staying
constant and the speed at which the head
moves is stay staying constant. So if I
gave you previously let's say like we go
back in year uh 2010
uh a typical disc would be like maybe
200 GB
and it has a certain throughput of how
much it can read. Now fast forward to
today's typical disk is like 6
terabytes.
So you your data center has a lot of
fewer disks to store the same amount of
data, but this this throughput is is is
like an order of magnitude less.
So and and and and you're coming to the
people responsible like on building data
centers and you say I need more discs
not for storage, I need more discs for
for throughput.
And you usually would hear an absurd
thing that says uh discs are very cheap
like compared to everything else in the
data center super cheap but you cannot
get them you know you cannot easily go
and buy like a few thousand discs and
and and easily install them like you
need racks you need power you need you
know
yeah it it it just uh it's similar to
how like during COVID we all ran out of
toilet paper right like the stores just
couldn't couldn't like like why would
you run out of toilet paper, right? It's
just because it's bulky item that the
stores cannot easily store in the on the
shelves.
So that's that's roughly you you
mentioned having to predict 18 months
out how many TPUs you'd need. And I'm
curious when you look back on that
prediction of how many you needed, did
you over orderer or under orderer?
>> Usually under. Um we try to be
relatively conservative because uh like
your main goal is to make money, right?
Like with LLMs, if you look at this
current world of LLMs, they just order
more like we want more gigawatts of data
centers, they don't even really like
none none of these companies is
profitable with LLMs, right? They all
losing money and they're all fine with
that. But when you have a mature
business uh like ads you you need to be
making money on that. So if you if you
waste it uh you know if you
overprovisioned and uh this goes to
waste then it's not good. But then it
constrains what kind of models you can
train like also like models don't stay
the same. So when you're saying 18
months from now we'll not be training
what we're training today but you don't
know what you're going to be training
like you know the attention mechanism
wasn't in use
10 years ago right and suddenly it's
it's it's needed so like you you your
chip might not be even capable of doing
that uh so TPUs are quite specialized uh
hardware so they are not as generic as
GPUs
Um and there were certain things that uh
we had to work around a lot of times
like uh there were certain functionality
was very difficult to implement
>> like what? Yeah, embedding lookups uh in
certain types of embeddings where like
essentially the the chip is very good at
doing matrix multiplication
and uh accessing memory by big chunks of
memory and embeddings are things where
you need sparse uh access like you know
random access essentially and that's
that's difficult to do in the chip.
>> Yeah. One thing I want to ask cuz you
said you enjoy mentoring others and I
was curious, do you have favorite maybe
stories of mentorship or favorite advice
that you like to give when you're
mentoring other people?
>> Well, I once had an intern on the team.
I was also not very senior back then. I
was like L L4 maybe. And I had an intern
that I hosted and then later that intern
converted to full-timer and few years
later he became the manager of the team
that he interned in.
>> Oh, that's funny. Were you were you
reporting to him eventually?
>> No, I by that time I already switched
projects but uh don't underestimate your
interns. They can be really really good.
When you look back on your career, is
there any regret that you have that some
people could learn from or could help u
people avoid?
>> Not everything was very smooth in my
career, but uh I think it was still like
a learning experience like I wouldn't be
who I who I am today if I didn't go
through those uh periods of time. I was
very
uh idealistic when I was younger like I
believed that like Google is a really
positive force in the world that uh it's
really like you know I would work here
just because it's Google not because it
pays more like you know uh not not not
because of some like you know I really
wanted to be in Google because of my
personal values and uh how the company
operated and then I got disillusioned
over the years uh That's yes, it's it's
just a corporate like maybe in the as of
17 years ago it was really a more a
different company but today it's it is a
corporation.
Um just like any any other corporation
has positive things, it has negative
things but uh what matters to the
company at the end of the day is the
bottom line on the financial reports and
uh
uh you know they they will do whatever
it takes to to get there to increase
that number.
>> Is there something that led to that
disillusionment?
you know, Google had a lot of remote
offices, for example, and I was working
in the Pittsburgh office, uh, which was
relatively remote office, and they at
the same time they shut down an office
in Atlanta
and it was roughly the same size and uh,
it was quite shocking to everybody like
why would you shut down an office with a
few hundred people working there? And
the answer we got from the leadership
they said well we have those big uh
senior vice presidents of the company
who decide how to allocate the headcount
and where to invest like you know I want
to hire in Bay Area. I want to hire in
Seattle. I want to hire in this place.
And just as so happened that uh the big
lead who was sponsoring that Atlanta
office decided to pull out and nobody
else
uh was willing to take over uh the
headcount of that office. So it was just
like you you feel like yeah at the end
of the day I'm just a cell in the
spreadsheet
you know it's like
there was very little empathy that
company showed to those people. They
said like yeah we can help you relocate
if you want to to other places but uh if
not uh here's your exit package and good
luck and that was like many many years
ago before all the layoffs that happened
after co and
you know nowadays it's people are much
less uh it's it's much more
understandable that the company can lay
off anybody just because this this
project here doesn't make sense anymore.
we'll just like shut it down and let
people go. Like this is now a common
scene. It was not the case as of 10
years ago.
>> Yeah. I remember I think when Google was
a lot earlier, it was um you don't be
evil and the culture was very very set
on that.
>> Yeah, I think they still like they still
trying not to be evil but again the
bottom line often drives the overrides
that decision. I guess it's true for all
public companies. Yeah. And then the
last question I'd like to ask is um if
you could go back to when you just
entered the industry or you were working
at Google and give yourself some advice
knowing everything you know now, what
would you say? I worked on some projects
that uh didn't make sense to me in in
the essentially when I especially when I
was more junior like I I was working on
some projects that uh like why why are
we building this in the first place? Who
who needs this? And then uh a year later
the leadership realizes the same thing
and they just shut down the project. Uh
so so maybe work on what matters like
ask yourself like does my company really
benefit from what I'm doing like and and
if not then maybe you shouldn't be there
>> in that situation let's say you
recognized it and then your your org's
going in that direction you think it's
useless but you're a junior engineer
what what could you do to kind of adjust
your direction
>> I mean talk to other managers I find
another project.
There are diff different companies have
different uh treatment of people who
want to switch projects. Uh before
Google actually briefly worked at Intel,
their switching project was almost
impossible. Like it's it's much easier
to just quit and then reapply. Uh versus
Google was was very fluid. Like you
could easily switch projects within
Google. So this advice doesn't work for
any company. Like I know some companies
like IBM is another example I've heard
where switching projects is is
impossible. Yeah, some companies have
certain reputations. I I don't know.
I've never worked at at IBM, so I don't
know. But that's that's the reputation
they got. Within Google, it was easy to
switch projects. Within Meta, I believe
it's easy to switch projects.
I Yeah, I don't know about other
companies. Yeah, I think most modernday
comp or Silicon Valley companies are
inspired by Google, Meta, those types of
companies. So, similar culture on team
switches. So, awesome. Well, yeah,
thanks so much for your time, Eigor. I
really appreciate it.
>> Yeah, thank you very much. And yeah, I
hope somebody finds it useful.
>> Thanks for listening to the podcast. I
don't sell anything or do sponsorships,
but if you want to help out with the
podcast, you can support by engaging
with the content on YouTube or on
Spotify. If you want to drop a review,
that'll be super helpful. And if there's
any guests that you want to bring on to,
please let me know. I feel like sourcing
very senior IC's, there's no wellstudied
list out there on Google that I can just
search this up. So, if there's someone
in your org or at your company who you
really look up to and you want to hear
their career story, let me know and I'll
reach out to